Guide to the John W. Dyckman papers, 1959-1987
Dyckman, John W. papers, 1959-1987
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
John W. Dyckman Papers, 1959-1987
4382
John W. Dyckman
5.1 cubic ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts, project files, and documents
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, biographical materials, course outlines, project files, notes, drafts, lectures, articles, reports, and other writings relating to John W. Dyckman's professional activities.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Geography and Environmental Engineering, Urban Planning; Director, Johns Hopkins Center for Regional Development and Planning, Lille, France.
John W. Dyckman received a B.A. from Chicago Teachers College in 1944, and holds M.A. and Ph.D. degrees from the University of Chicago. He began working in the planning field in Chicago. During the 1950s he served as consultant to the American Council to Improve Neighborhoods, the New York City Planning Dept. for Capital Improvement Planning, and the National Park Service. From 1961 to 1963 he was Chief of the Urban and Regional Economic Development section of Arthur D. Little company in San Francisco. Beginning in 1965, he worked extensively in the U.S. and overseas, serving as Field Director of the American-Yugoslav Project in Ljubljana, in Israel, Italy, Colombia, Panama, and Egypt. Beginning in 1975 he was a consultant to the Region of Ile de France (Paris), and worked on a number of domestic planning projects as well. He taught a number of American university courses, eventually becoming the James Irvine Professor of Urban and Regional Planning at the University of Southern California. He was a member of the Los Angeles Chapter of Lambda Alpha.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence; biographical materials; course outlines; project files; notes, drafts, lectures, articles, reports, and other writings relating to John W. Dyckman's professional activities.
Correspondence and papers relating to the work of John Dyckman and Allan Blackman relating to a project of the Center for Planning and Development Research at the University of California at Berkeley sponsored by the United States Public Health Service to survey "scientific knowledge about the interaction of human behavior with metropolitan environments," and a conference on "The Role of Science in Environmental Planning," held on May 24-27, 1966, sponsored by the USPHS, Berkeley, and the American Institute of Planners.
Part of Lambda Alpha Archives.
Part of Regional Science Archives.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Dyckman, John W.; Lambda Alpha International. Los Angeles Chapter.
Subjects:
City planning.; Regional science.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Biographical Information (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous Professional Papers (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Travel (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Course Outlines, Bibliographies (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1981-1983; re: general activities (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Governor?s Advisory Commission on Housing Problems, 1962; Draft (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions, Santa Barbara, Nov. 16, 1963; Talk by JWD (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Governor?s Advisory Commission on Housing Problems, 1962; Draft (Box 1, Folder 8)
- State Planning, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Altshuler & Logue: Cautionary Tales for Planners", 1967, 1982; (Review ? Journal), American Institute of Planners (AIP) (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Social Planning in an American Democracy", 1968; (AIP Conference) (Box 1, Folder 11)
- American-Yugoslav Project, 1971; Draft (Box 1, Folder 12)
- American-Yugoslav Report, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Vietnam Project, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Center for Comparative Urbanism, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Evaluation des Objectifs et Strategies del la Planification et de la Region Parisienne?", 1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Bahrain, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Italy, ca. 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- 1st Congreso Internacional, 1980; de Planeacion de Grandes Cuidades (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Notes and Reports, 1981; (Congreso Internacional de Planeacion de Grandes Ciudades) (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Egypt, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Delta Partnership, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Ad Hoc Group on Urban Problems, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Ad Hoc Group on Urban Problems (2), 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Ad Hoc group on Urban Problems (3), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Task Force on Coordination of State/Regional Planning in Maryland; Other Projects, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Panama Project - Memos, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Mexico, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Metro Center Activities, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Public Policy Program, Metro Center, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Public Policy Program, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Task Force on Economic Development, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- France, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Nord/Pas de Calais, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Johns Hopkins Center, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Lille, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- "Planning in an Unprepared Environment" - Bahrain, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Review Articles (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Collaborative Efforts (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Articles (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Articles A-1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Articles A-1 (2) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Articles A-1 (3) (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Articles J-Z (1) (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Articles J-Z (2) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Articles J-Z (3) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Manuscripts, Miscellaneous, (Incomplete) (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Technology - AIP, Writings & Speeches by JWD (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous Writings (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous Writings and Papers (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Policy Analysis and Planning:, Transdisciplinary Concepts and Approaches (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "Introduction to Readings in the Theory of Planning", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- "Economic Aspects of the Vietnam War", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- "An Evaluation of the Columbian Urban Sector Loan", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- "Successes and Failures in Regional Development Programs: A Comparative Prospective", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- "Employment Implications of Changing Economic Structure in the U.S.", ca. 1980; Research Proposal (Box 2, Folder 19)
- "Notes on the 10th International Fellows Conference", 1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- The Two Cultures of Planning, 1983; Draft (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Lecture Series Drafts (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Drafts and Writings (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Drafts, Notes and Writings (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Notes (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Notes on Urban Regional Reorganization (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Notes (Box 2, Folder 27-30)
- Annotated Hearings - Subcommittee on Science, Research and Development, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Notebooks (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Notebooks (Box 2, Folder 33)
- "Public Administration Review" (PAR), Volume No. 3, May/June, 1971 (Box 3)
- Metropolis in Crisis, 1971; Edited by J.K. Hadden, L. H. Masotti, C.J. Larson. Second edition. (Box 3)
- "Spatial Policies for Regional Development: A Demonstration Study of the Ljubljana Region", Jan. 1970; Technical Report, Numbers 4, 6, 7, 11, 12 (Part I), 12, (Part II). (Box 3)
- "Information Needs of the New Planning System,", Nov. 1970; Report of Joint Local Authority. S.D.D. and M.H.L.G. Study Team. Draft. (Box 3)
- "Structure of Influence in Local Communities," by Janez Jerovsek, 1969; Research Reports. (Box 3)
- "International Planning Workshop", 1969; Proceedings and selected papers from the Urbanistic Institute of SR Slovenia. (Box 3)
- "Toward a Methodology for Regional Planning:, 1968; the Proposal and Evaluation of Alternative Patterns of Spatial Organization for the Ljubljana Urban Region." Volume 1, Description and Program. (Box 3)
- "Cities, Their Origin, Growth and Human Impact,", Readings from Scientific American. (Box 3)
- Guest Editor?s Introduction:, Sept. 1969; "The Practical Uses of Planning Theory," by John W. Dyckman. Reprinted from Journal of the American Institute of Planners. (Box 3)
- "Water and Choice in the Colorado Basin:, 1968; An Example of Alternatives in Water Management." A Report by the Committee on Water of the National Research Council. Publication No. 1689. (Box 3)
- Advanced Study Program: The Urban Policy Conference Program, Oct. 1968; The American City Seminar in Association with A Consortium of Colleges and the City of Memphis. (Box 3)
- "Status of the Inquiry Into Bay Area Regional Organization,", August 1968; A Research Progress Report to the Technical Advisory Committee of the Joint Committee on Bay Area Regional Organization. (Box 3)
- Annotated article from Daedalus, Summer 1966; Journal of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. (Box 3)
- ?Tradition and Change," in Daedalus, Summer 1966 (Box 3)
- "Cities," in Scientific American, Sept. 1965 (Box 3)
- Community Facilities: Social Values and Goals in Planning For Education, Health, and Recreation, Sept. 1965; One typescript manuscript. (Box 3)
- ?The Future Metropolis," in Daedalus, Winter 1961 (Box 3)
- Readings in Planning and Decision Theory, Edited by Douglass B. Lee, Jr. Department of City and Regional Planning, University of California at Berkeley. (Box 3)
- "International Professional Exchange: The Implications of the American-Yugoslav Project", Jan. 1977; The Johns Hopkins University Center for Metropolitan Planning and Research. (Box 4)
- "Transfer of U.S. Planning Technologies,", April 1973; J.W.D., University of California at Berkeley. The Peter B. Andrews Memorial Lecture. (Box 4)
- "The Administration and Provision of Urban Services in Grand Rapids, Michigan and Ljubljana, Yugoslavia:, April 1975; A Report of the Grand Rapids-Ljubljana Comparative Urban Study." (Box 4)
- "Evaluation Des Objectifs et Strategies de la Planification et de L?Amenagerent de la Region Parisienne, avec une Reference Particuliere au Schema Directeur de la Region,", JWD and S. Cohen. (Box 4)
- "L?Amenagement et le Secteur des Services dans la Region Parisienne,", Nov. 1973; Stephen Cohen and JWD. (Box 4)
- "Conservation of Energy in Transportation Round Table,", March 1974; Washington, D.C., A Scientific American Conference. (Box 4)
- "International Collaboration in Planning Research: Summary Report of the Ljubljana Region Demonstration Study,", April 1972; American-Yugoslav Project in Regional and Urban Planning Studies. (Box 4)
- "Thu Thiem Peninsula Development Plan,", Sept. 1972; Agency for International Development Contract (AID). (Box 4)
- Monthly Report No. 2, Thu Thiem Peninsula Development, Saigon, Vietnam, Dec. 1971; Agency for International Development (AID). (Box 4)
- "Proposal to the Department of Interior for the Analysis of the Restoration of Historic Buildings in Terms of Energy, Labor and Urban Historical District Revitalization,", August 1977; by Urban Design Disciplines, Inc., Kaplan/McLaughlin and the Energy Group. (Box 4)
- "Proposal and Qualifications for Planning Services for the Tahoe Regional Planning Agency.", Oct. 1977; South Lake Tahoe, California. (Box 4)
- Report of the International Ministers? Colloquium on National Strategies for Urban Policy, Sept. 1980; Sponsored by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development and The Johns Hopkins University. (Box 4)
- "Planning the Planning Process: A Case Study.", Johns Hopkins University, Center for Metropolitan Planning and Research. (Box 4)
- A Summary Report of the Tenth International Fellows Conference: ?The Changing Metropolitan Economy of the Eighties.", Fall 1980; Johns Hopkins Center for Metropolitan Planning and Research. (Box 4)
- "Decentralization: A Framework for Policy Analysis," by S. Cohen, JWD, E. Schoenberger and C.R. Downs, Feb. 1981; Project on Managing Decentralization performed between the University of California at Berkeley and the U.S. Agency for International Development (AID). (Box 4)
- "Primer Congreso Internacional de Planeacion de Grandes Cuidades. Resumen y Conclusiones,", June 1981; Departamento del Distrito Federal, Mexico. (Box 4)
- "Seminar Discussion of Committee on Urban Public Economics,", March 1985; reported by John Aiken. (Box 4)
- First Annual Report, Centre European Johns Hopkins for Regional Planning and Research, Nord-Pas De Calais, March 1985; The Center for Metropolitan Planning and Research at the Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland. (Box 4)
- La Propuesta para El Estudio de la Viabilidad del Desarrollo de un Mayor Centro de Recreo en Nicaragua, para El Gobierno de Nicaragua, el Ministerio de Ceonomia, Industria, y Comercio, ca. 1972; Preparado par The Tourplan Partnership. (Box 4)
- Citation:, April 1964; Election of JWD to membership in Lambda Alpha Honorary Professional Land Economics Fraternity. (Box 4)
- Cassette tape, "ACSP, Chicago, Prof. John W. Dyckman, Oct. 1982", tr-9914 (Box 5)
- The Metropolis in Transition, edited by ervin Y. Galantay, 1987 (Box 5)
- The 1964 Jennings Scholar Lectures, Sponsored By the Martha Holden Jennigns Foundation, 1965 (Box 5)
- Strategic Perspectives on Planning Practice, Barry Checkoway, 1986 (Box 5)
- Confidential papers of John W. Dyckman PH.D., 1983-1987 (Box 5)
- Daedalus, Summer 1966 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Articles, papers, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Articles, papers, 1967-1968; n.d. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Bibliography, Spring 1965 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- book chapter, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Reprint series, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Interview, 5/25/66 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Interview, 5/26/66 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Interview, 5/27/66 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Environment and Behavior, August 1969 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Report on conference on Planning and Managing the Residential Environment Cincinnati I, 4/18-19/1969 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Report on conference on Planning and Managing the Residential Environment Cincinnati II, 4/18-19/1969 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Final Draft of Paper for AIP-USPHS Project, 1/1966 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- An Environmental Approach to Human Stress and Well-being, Carson and Driver, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- How Should we measure Economic benefits from Public Health services? Linnenberg Epidemiologic Considerations of the Health of Urban Communities. Stallones, Commentary on Papers Prepared for the Epidemiological Center for Planning and Development research. Stallones, 1963,1966 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Richad Meier paper and editorial correspondence, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Environmental Planning Hufschmidt; The application of scientific data to planning theory, deGroot; Comments on "The Pattern of Streets", by Christopher Alexander, Carson; Black Culture and the planning of a pluralist environment, Berger, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Mathematical models of the urban environment, fiering: unidentified paper, A parsonian theory of traffic accidents, Stinchcombe; Policies for urban settlement intended to minimize losses from conflict and violence, Meier, 1966,1967 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Correspondence and misc. conference materials (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Fear and the House-as-haven in the Lower Class, Rainwater: Allen Blackmen Correspondence re conference papers, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Allen Blackman memos to J.W.D. re Conference papers (Box 7, Folder 16)